So this is my niece.
هذه بنت اخي
Her name is Yahli.
اسمها ياوي
She is nine months old.
عمرها 9 أشهر
Her mum is a doctor, and her dad is a lawyer.
والدتها طبيبة وأبوها محامي
By the time Yahli goes to college,
في الوقت الذي ستذهب فيه ياوي الي الكلية
the jobs her parents do are going to look dramatically different.
وظائف والديها ستختلف بشكل كبير
In 2013, researchers at Oxford University did a study on the future of work.
في 2013 , قام باحثون فى جامعة اكسفورد بعمل دراسة حول مستقبل العمل
They concluded that almost one in every two jobs have a high risk
وخلاصة ذلك أنه: وظيفة من كل وظيفتين تقريبا معرضة لخطر
of being automated by machines.
الاستبدال بالآلات
Machine learning is the technology
تعلم الآلة هي التكنولوجيا
that's responsible for most of this disruption.
المسؤوله عن معظم هذا الاضطراب
It's the most powerful branch of artificial intelligence.
إنها أقوى فروع الذكاء الاصطناعي
It allows machines to learn from data
إنها تسمح للآلات بالتعلم من البيانات
and mimic some of the things that humans can do.
و تقليد بعض الأشياء التى يفعلها الانسان
My company, Kaggle, operates on the cutting edge of machine learning.
شركتي - كاجل - تعمل علي أحدث تقنيات تعلم الآلة
We bring together hundreds of thousands of experts
جمعنا مئات الالاف من الخبراء
to solve important problems for industry and academia.
لحل المشاكل الهامة فى مجال الصناعة والأوساط الأكاديمية
This gives us a unique perspective on what machines can do,
وهذا يعطينا منظورا فريدًا لما تستطيع الآلات فعله
what they can't do
وما لا تستطيع فعله
and what jobs they might automate or threaten.
وما الوظائف التي يمكن للآلات أن تؤديها أو تهددها
Machine learning started making its way into industry in the early '90s.
بدأ مجال تعلم الآلات شق طريقه في الصناعة في وقت مبكرمن أوائل التسعينيات
It started with relatively simple tasks.
لقد بدأ بمهام بسيطة نسبيًا
It started with things like assessing credit risk from loan applications,
بدأ بأشياء مثل تقييم المخاطر الائتمانية من طلبات القروض
sorting the mail by reading handwritten characters from zip codes.
فرز البريد عن طريق قراءة الرموز البريدي المكتوبة بخط اليد
Over the past few years, we have made dramatic breakthroughs.
على مدى السنوات القليلة الماضية، أحرزنا تقدماً كبيراً
Machine learning is now capable of far, far more complex tasks.
الآلة الآن قادرة علي القيام بمهام أكثر تعقيدًا بكثير
In 2012, Kaggle challenged its community
في 2012 ، قامت "كاجل" بتحدّي عامليها
to build an algorithm that could grade high-school essays.
لبناء خوارزمية يمكنها أن تقيّم مقالات طلاب المدرسة الثانوية
The winning algorithms were able to match the grades
استطاعت الخوارزميات الفائزة أن تتطابق مع الدرجات
given by human teachers.
التي وضعها المعلمون البشر
Last year, we issued an even more difficult challenge.
في العام الماضي، أعلنا عن تحدي أكثر صعوبة
Can you take images of the eye and diagnose an eye disease
هل يمكنك التقاط صور للعين وتشخيص مرض في العين؟
called diabetic retinopathy?
يسمي اعتلال الشبكية السكري
Again, the winning algorithms were able to match the diagnoses
مرة أخرى، الخوارزميات الفائزة كانت قادرة على مطابقة التشخيصات
given by human ophthalmologists.
التي قدمها أطباء العيون البشر
Now, given the right data, machines are going to outperform humans
الآ، وبإعطاء البيانات الصحيحة، سوف تتفوق الاجهزة علي البشر
at tasks like this.
في مهام مثل هذه
A teacher might read 10,000 essays over a 40-year career.
المعلم يمكنه ان يقرأ 10,000 مقالة علي مدى 40 عام من التدريس
An ophthalmologist might see 50,000 eyes.
طبييب العيون يمكنه أن يكشف على 50,000 عين
A machine can read millions of essays or see millions of eyes
الآلة يمكنها قراءة ملايين المقالات أو تشخّص ملايين العيون
within minutes.
في غضون دقائق
We have no chance of competing against machines
ليس لدينا أي فرصة للتنافس مع الآلات
on frequent, high-volume tasks.
في المهام المتكررة، ذات الحجم الكبير
But there are things we can do that machines can't do.
ولكن، هناك أشياء نستطيع فعلها بينما لا تستطيع الآلات فعلها
Where machines have made very little progress
لم تحرز الآلات تقدماً كبيراً
is in tackling novel situations.
في مواجهة المواقف الجديدة
They can't handle things they haven't seen many times before.
لا يمكنها التعامل مع الاشياء التي لم تتعرض لها من قبل مرات عديدة
The fundamental limitations of machine learning
القيود الأساسية لتعلم الآلة
is that it needs to learn from large volumes of past data.
هى أنها تحتاج الى التعلم من كميات كبيرة من البيانات السابقة
Now, humans don't.
البشر ليسوا كذلك
We have the ability to connect seemingly disparate threads
لدينا القدرة على ربط أشياء تبدو متفرقة
to solve problems we've never seen before.
لحل مشاكل لم نواجهها من قبل
Percy Spencer was a physicist working on radar during World War II,
كان بيرسي سبنسر- الفيزيائي - يعمل على رادار خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية
when he noticed the magnetron was melting his chocolate bar.
عندما لاحظ أن صمام مغناطيس الرادار قد أذاب لوح الشوكولاتة الخاص به
He was able to connect his understanding of electromagnetic radiation
وكان قادرا على توصيل فهمه للإشعاع الكهرومغناطيسي
with his knowledge of cooking
مع معرفته في الطبخ
in order to invent -- any guesses? -- the microwave oven.
من أجل اختراع -- أية تخمينات؟ -- فرن المايكرويف
Now, this is a particularly remarkable example of creativity.
الآن، هذا مثال واضح على الإبداع
But this sort of cross-pollination happens for each of us in small ways
ولكن هذا النوع من التلاقح يحدث لكل واحد منا علي مستويات أصغر
thousands of times per day.
آلاف المرات في اليوم الواحد
Machines cannot compete with us
لا يمكن للآلات أن تنافسنا
when it comes to tackling novel situations,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالتعامل مع مواقف جديدة
and this puts a fundamental limit on the human tasks
وهذا يضع حدا أساسيا لمهام الإنسان
that machines will automate.
التي ستُسبدل بالآلات
So what does this mean for the future of work?
فماذا يعني هذا بالنسبة لمستقبل العمل؟
The future state of any single job lies in the answer to a single question:
مستقبل أي وظيفة يكمن في إجابة على سؤال واحد:
To what extent is that job reducible to frequent, high-volume tasks,
إلى أي مدى يمكن تفكيك هذا العمل إالى مهام متكرره، وكبيرة الحجم
and to what extent does it involve tackling novel situations?
وإلى أي مدى ينطوي الأمر على التعامل مع مواقف جديدة؟
On frequent, high-volume tasks, machines are getting smarter and smarter.
فيما يتعلق بالمهام المتكرره، ذات الحجم الكبير فإن الآلات تزداد ذكاءاُ أكثر فأكثر
Today they grade essays. They diagnose certain diseases.
اليوم تقوم الآلات بتقييم المقالات وتشخيص بعض الأمراض
Over coming years, they're going to conduct our audits,
وعلى مدى السنوات القادمة، سوف يقومون بإجراء عمليات تدقيق حساباتنا
and they're going to read boilerplate from legal contracts.
وسيقومون بقراءة نصوص من العقود القانونية
Accountants and lawyers are still needed.
لا تزال هناك حاجة للمحاسبين والمحامين
Now, as mentioned,
الآن، وكما ذكرنا
machines are not making progress on novel situations.
فإن الآلات لا تحرز تقدما في التعامل مع المواقف الجديدة
The copy behind a marketing campaign needs to grab consumers' attention.
تدشين حملة تسويقية يحتاج إلى جذب انتباه المستهلكين
It has to stand out from the crowd.
والتميز عن الاخرين
Business strategy means finding gaps in the market,
تعني استراتيجيات الأعمال العثور على الثغرات الموجودة في السوق
things that nobody else is doing.
أشياء لا يقم بها أي شخص
It will be humans that are creating the copy behind our marketing campaigns,
سيكون البشر هم من وراء حملات التسويق التي نقوم بها
and it will be humans that are developing our business strategy.
وسيكون البشر هم من يقومون بتطوير استراتيجيات الاعمال
So Yahli, whatever you decide to do,
حتى "ياهلي"، أياً كان ما تقررين القيام به
let every day bring you a new challenge.
دعي كل يوم يجلب تحدياً جديداً
If it does, then you will stay ahead of the machines.
وإن حدث كذلك، فستبقين أفضل من الآلات
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)